<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Quaking principles dashed in pieces by the standing and unshaken truth. Being an examination of the tenents held forth by certain northern people, viz. 1. Slighting of the written word. 2. A speaking to that within man. 3. Denying the use of reason in the matters of God. 4. A denying of the ascension and being of the body of Christ. 5. A denying of all the ordinances of Christ. 6. A denying honour to men. 7. Affording absolute perfection at one instant. / By Henoch Howet.</title>
            <author>Howet, Enoch.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E821_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866415</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866415</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118688</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86646)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118688)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 125:E821[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Quaking principles dashed in pieces by the standing and unshaken truth. Being an examination of the tenents held forth by certain northern people, viz. 1. Slighting of the written word. 2. A speaking to that within man. 3. Denying the use of reason in the matters of God. 4. A denying of the ascension and being of the body of Christ. 5. A denying of all the ordinances of Christ. 6. A denying honour to men. 7. Affording absolute perfection at one instant. / By Henoch Howet.</title>
                  <author>Howet, Enoch.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills, and are to be sold at his House near Py-corner at the sign of Sir John Oldcastle.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118688:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Quaking Principles daſhed in pieces by the ſtanding and unſhaken TRUTH.</p>
            <p>Being an Examination of the Tenents held forth by certain Northern People, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Slighting of the written Word.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>A ſpeaking to that within Man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Denying the uſe of Reaſon in the matters of God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>A denying of the Aſcenſion and Being of the Body of</hi> Chriſt.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>A denying of all the Ordinances of</hi> Chriſt.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>A denying Honor to Men.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>Affording abſolute perfection at one inſtant.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Henoch Howet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Houſe near <hi>Py-corner</hi> at the Sign of Sir <hi>John Oldcaſtle.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118688:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118688:2"/>
            <head>Quaking Principles daſhed in pieces by the ſtanding and unſhaken Truth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He God of the whole Earth now being about to declare his glorie to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as that the Iſles that have not heard of his fame ſhould be brought in to ſee his glorie, and and the Kingdoms of this world being about to become the Lords and his <hi>Christs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Satan at ſuch a time is doubtleſs ſtanding at the right hand of our <hi>Joſhua,</hi> to reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>At the right hand, not at the left, for he will take the better hand that he may be more eminent in ſhew, and be preferred, in the view of the world, before the <hi>Joſhua's</hi> of God, they muſt come in a lower place, on the left hand, in a more carnal way in the eye of the world, and in the report of thoſe that ſpeak by ſwelling words of ſpiritualneſs, calling the God of this world that blindeth the eys, a God of light, and all this darkneſs, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alneſs; at this time I ſay appeareth thoſe times that if it were poſſible ſhould deceive the very elect, whereby the ſtars are drawn from Heaven and caſt unto the Earth.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I have thought it my dutie to ſerve the Land of my Nativitie, or rather men fearing God in this Nation, in ſingling out certain ſpecious Deceits of Satans; and as <hi>Christ</hi> my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter did to Satan, reproving them with this infallible authoritie, <hi>It is written;</hi> a ſpeech that can hardly be endured with theſe pretended ſpiritual men, for that Satan being overthrown by it by the Saviour of men, is now fain to flie to unwritten notions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting,
<list>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118688:3"/>
                  <item>1. A ſlighting of the written Word.</item>
                  <item>2. A ſpeaking to that within you. It is their phraſe.</item>
                  <item>3. A denying of the uſe of Reaſon, and conſideration in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God, calling it Serpent and <hi>Adam, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Denying of the Aſcenſion or Being of the Bodie of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. A denying of all Ordinances of <hi>Christ.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. A denying honor to men.</item>
                  <item>7. Abſolute perfection at one inſtant.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, they oppoſe the Word <hi>[Christ]</hi> to the written Word, and will a Word that is a Diſcoverie ſpiritual to be the Word. But whatſoever it is that they call the Word, it is perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe and not the truth, although it be conceived in the ſoul of a <hi>Paul,</hi> except the Scriptures will approve of it, or it be ſo in Scriptures, that is to ſay, the ſame that is recorded in Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. <hi>Paul</hi> counts it true Nobilitie to be daily conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in Scripture, for the proof of revealed truths, and (as they count) is carnalneſs and lowneſs; for a man at one of their meetings pulling a Bible out of his pocket, one of them asked, What doth that man with that Book there?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again, it is not onely the being of the bodie of <hi>Christ,</hi> but the actions and undertakings of <hi>Christ</hi> alſo that is profitable to us. And of theſe the Scripture keepeth a record, therefore glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to ſurmiſe any thing of <hi>Christ,</hi> which Scripture recordeth not, is to ſtand at the right hand of our <hi>Joſhua,</hi> to reſiſt the work of God, and to be more excellent and more glorious than plain Scripture. <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf ſaith, I come to fulfill whatſoever is written in the Law and the Prophets, and the ſayings concerning me. Being the Apoſtle chargeth the plain ſimple ſheep of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaying, Let no man perſwade you above what is written.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Again if ignorance of the Scripture be the ground of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, <hi>Mark</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.29 how do theſe men drive the people in darkneſs, that works upon the people to cauſe a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteem of the Scriptures, and yet forcibly perſwade them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Doctrine? Conſider, do not the Papiſts denie us the Scriptures in our mother Tongue that their unwritten verities might take place? And now the ſame ſpirit in another appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance perſwades us to the uſeleſneſs of the Scriptures, that his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual deluſions might take place though in another form.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118688:3"/>O ſubtle Devil! Will nothing ſerve thy turn but to diſarm us and take away that weapon that <hi>Christ</hi> fought and overthrew thee with? But as he had the victorie, ſo muſt all his members in their overcoming ſtrength obtain it, (I mean with this authoritie, <hi>It is written.</hi>) Then thou mightſt ſleep quietly in the hearts of thine, in thy luſts, in thy envie, in thine idolatrie, in thy pride, in all luxurie and uncleanneſs, if there were not an <hi>[It is written]</hi> to diſquiet thee. Men could not know luſt but by <hi>[It is written] Rom.</hi> 7.7. If thou canſt do this thy ſeven ſpirits ſhall dwell qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, and thou maiſt exalt thy ſelf above God. And thy Angels may appear more glorious than plain Preachers of the Goſpel without controll.</p>
            <p>Again, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. The perfect furniſhing the man of God to all good works is the end that the Scriptures were given for, and the uſe of them is to reprove, to correct, to inſtruct in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. The Author of them is God, by the inſpiration of God, (that is to ſay) in the hearts of the Prophets and Apoſtles. For the Propheſies of old, that are called Scripture, are the movings of the Spirit of God in the holy men of God: 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. And our foundation is laid upon the Prophets and Apoſtles, (which is their Doctrine) <hi>Christ</hi> being the head-corner-ſtone. So that if Satan could take away or vilifie Scripture, he would hinder man exceedingly from being throughly furniſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Take away the profitable means of this Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> reproof, correction, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. O! how would he bring in a floud of deſtruction, by filling mankinde with ignorance and luſtfull pleaſures, in taking off the Bridle that checks Luſt. It brings in a Night of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that men might take their pleaſure in ſin without any Light at all to ſhame them for it, if he could make the Scriptures uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. To ſhake us in our foundation, I mean the Doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles, would make the whole building of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Godlineſs fall. O ſubtle Serpent! the Lord rebuke thee. If wiſdom to ſalvation through faith in <hi>Christ</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Scripture 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. Then what a ſweet conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and harmonie do we finde here betwixt the written Rule and the active life of a believer; Who but Satan or his inſtruments dare ſlight the one, and affirm he regards the other?</p>
            <p>Again, if the Scriptures are the means of comfort and hope,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118688:4"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. How exceedingly were we wronged if any mans of our comfort or hope ſhould be taken from us? For comfort and hope they are in two reſpects. Firſt, what cauſe of comfort is there when all our experiences are the ſame that have been of old declared in Scripture. And if Satan in the time of Gods withdrawing ſhould go about to perſwade us that our experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences were falſe, and we would ſay they were revealed from God, and the ſame that were written in the Scriptures of truth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.21. What a comfort would that be to us? Note here in this place of <hi>Daniel</hi> when the Angel would comfort him, he doth it not onely by touching his lips, by lifting him up, by ſpeaking to him, but alſo that he might ſeal up all his experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; he ſaith, I will ſhew thee what is written in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, of a truth there is none that holdeth with us but <hi>Michael</hi> your Prince.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reſpect wherein we are comforted by Scripture is, in reſpect of our exſpectation, when we hope for nothing but what God hath in Scripture promiſed; this makes us come boldly to the Throne of Grace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. I <hi>Daniel</hi> underſtand by Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and I ſet my face to ſeek the Lord by prayers and ſupplications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and when things come to paſs that God hath promiſed, it fils the heart with praiſes, and will make all that have <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit to ſay, In God will I praiſe thy Word.</p>
            <p>But now leſt ſome ſhould ſay, that I make the Scriptures the ſole cauſe of knowledg, which the Saints are to look unto for Life and Salvation.</p>
            <p>I anſwer No, I minde them to be but the teſtimonie of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but yet ſuch a teſtimonie as is able in the hand of the eternal Teacher to make the man of God wiſe to Salvation; yet if we come not to <hi>Christ</hi> by the drawing of the Father we can have no ſaving life nor light, although we have the whole outward knowledg of them in the written letter, <hi>John</hi> 5.39.</p>
            <p>Sure it is, they that were inſtructed by <hi>Moſes</hi> had the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teachings of the now written letter, and ſo ſtill; for the organ of the ear or eye letteth into the underſtanding whileſt God applieth it to the heart; and by this means the Saints in the hand of God are humbled at his feet to receive of his Word, as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.3. Though <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake theſe words of Chriſtian ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118688:4"/>
yet they adminiſtred to the ear that ſweet dropping ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.33. which by the Spirit of God applying, is made powerfull in operation, and is now left alſo upon record for our inſtruction according to that of <hi>Christ,</hi> who ſaith, They have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, when they had but the words which <hi>Moſes</hi> writ. The Scriptures prove the work of the new birth, counſels us to buy of God milk and wine, and teacheth us to bear the hand of the Lord patiently, till he bring us forth to the light, and ſhew us his righteouſneſs, <hi>Micah</hi> 7. from the 7. to the 9. <hi>v.</hi> It teacheth us perſeverance to the end, and he that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and knoweth this, except he do it, it availeth nothing, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31, 32. And divers ſweet directions and promiſes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with records of Saints former experiences, all which appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Gods ſpirit to the believers heart is able to make the man of God wiſe to Salvation.</p>
            <p>And now I come to the ſecond of their miſtakes, that is, A ſpeaking to a thing within thee. I would fain know what can be meant by the thing within men; for there is nothing in man to be ſpoken to but man; if it be Light it hath enlightned man, and then man is to be accounted and ſpoken to as enlightned; ſo then they cannot ſpeak to his Light as diſtinct, but to man enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; for <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles always ſpoke to man. It's true Satan that hath ſent forth his Angels, transforming himſelf into Angels of Light, to publiſh his deluſions and deceits, may and it's likely hath therewithall ſent forth a ſpirit in men to perſwade the receiving that his dark and deluſive Light; and hereupon the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of Satan without may ſpeak to the ſpirit of Satan within under the notion of Light: but unleſs they ſpeak unto Satan or ſome of his Legion in man, I know not how they can ſpeak unto any Light in man diſtinct from him. It may be his language, but it is none of Gods, for it's no form of ſound words which we are commanded to hold faſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            <p>And now I come to the third of their miſtakes, that is, The denying the uſe of reaſon or conſideration in the matters of God, calling it Serpentine and many other terms of contempt: and upon this ground they will not do as the Apoſtles of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf who did diſpute or reaſon with the gain-ſayers of the truth. <hi>Christ</hi> diſputed with the <hi>Jews,</hi> 6, 8. <hi>chap.</hi> of <hi>John,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118688:5"/>
and <hi>Stephen, Acts</hi> 6.9, 10. There aroſe certain of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue called <hi>Libertines,</hi> and <hi>Cyrenians,</hi> and <hi>Alexandrians,</hi> and of <hi>Cilicia</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> and diſputed with <hi>Stephen;</hi> and they were not able to reſiſt the wiſdom and ſpirit by which he ſpake. And why was it, but becauſe of the ſtrength of demonſtration that was in it? The Spirit of God makes uſe of reaſon, or wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and tongue, in man, and all the faculties of bodie and ſoul in a godly man to honor himſelf, and to reſiſt unto bloud, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving againſt ſin, and to contend earneſtly for the faith once given to the Saints. So that ye ſee how far different theſe men are from the words and practice of <hi>Christ</hi> and his miniſtrie. As for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon carnally implied we juſtifie it not, which hath this character, it is pitying it ſelf; and therein Satan is converſant; for when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Christ,</hi> Maſter, pitie thy ſelf, none of theſe things ſhall befall thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for this Reaſon where it rules, will not let any follow God or <hi>Christ</hi> further than they can carrie their own things, <hi>viz.</hi> their own honors, pleaſures, eaſe, worldly beloveds, that their worldly luſts may have life and delight, and ſo throw by the things of <hi>Christ,</hi> his Croſs, his afflictions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently his Crown too; this made the Apoſtle complain, All men ſeek their own things, and none the things of <hi>Christ.</hi> We allow and honor reaſon in conſidering the works of God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.13. As thus, in ſo much that God hath made one creature, I mean the Air that is preſent in all places at once, and without it no creature that hath life can live. And another creature to give light to the whole frame of nature, I mean the Sun; How eaſie a thing then is it by reaſon to conclude this God to be in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at once viewing wickedneſs, and creating new hearts, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving light to all, though they ſit in darkneſs and in the ſhadow of death? Like to this <hi>David</hi> reaſons, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 94 9, 10 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In ſo much that God is the Author of all memorie and wiſdom, whereby all things in the earth may be remembred, ſome things by one, ſome things by another, ſome things by a third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all this is by the virtue of Gods working, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How eaſie a thing it is for the wicked ſinning wretch to his conviction or ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to believe from reaſon God is able both to remember and take account of all his ſins, and to ſet them before him at the day of judgment?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118688:5"/>3. Conſidering that God hath created the whole world in ſix days; how eaſie a thing is it, conclude that he is able to ſend down the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from above, according to the Word, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. And let thoſe be ſilent that ask, where ſhall there be room at the Reſurrection for all to ſtand? for as they are not able to comprehend what was ſpoken of before, till it was brought to paſs; ſo neither are they able to comprehend how there ſhall be room more than they are able to create room for thoſe that ſhall appear to judgment. But we allow not that Reaſon that will not let the Word run and be glorified, but reproach it and ſpeak againſt it, as thoſe that believe not Election but ſtand que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning the juſtice of God, as if God could be no further juſt than they could ſee him juſt. Theſe do in effect denie his Name, Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull; for they would have him ſo little and narrow a God, that they are able to defend him; or elſe they would think it their part to ſtand ſtill and wonder, when they cannot ſee through his juſtice, and not ask how they ſhould defend his juſtice, when any thing exceeds the compaſs of their reaſon. <hi>Paul</hi> thought theſe perſons not worthy of an anſwer, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19, 20. and therefore he takes them off ſhort, ſaying, Nay, but who art thou, O man, that replieſt againſt God? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Neither do we allow of that reaſoning which will take a Text of Scripture and raiſe an argument from it, and thereupon conclude their own ſalvation, and ſo get a concluſion inſtead of <hi>Christ</hi> for their aſſurance, when as the Scripture telleth us it muſt be wrought out, ſaying, Work out your ſalvation with fear and trembling; for <hi>Christ</hi> is to be noted for to be manifeſted to his, <hi>John</hi> 14 21. revealed in <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16. And therefore let us know that there is a day to dawn, and a day ſtar to riſe in our hearts, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. all which we are in prayers to be violent for, and wait patiently for. This is the good uſe of reaſon, to reſiſt the gain ſayers of truth, in diſputes, to be readie always to give anſwer to every man that asketh a reaſon of the hope that is in us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. and to taſte of the goodneſs of God till we have loſt our ſelves in it, and to crie out with <hi>Paul, O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledg of God! How unſearchable are his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his ways paſt finding out? Rom.</hi> 11.33.</p>
            <p>And now I come to the fourth of their miſtakes, <hi>viz.</hi> Their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118688:6"/>
denying of the Aſcerſion or the Being of the Bodie of <hi>Christ;</hi> under the pretence of this Scripture, Fleſh and Bloud cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom of Heaven. It is true that fleſh and bloud without the Spirit and Life of God cannot; but he that is joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God is one ſpirit; ſo if we ſhould ſay, This bulk, or lump, or form of man or mans fleſh could not continue upon the earth, it were true, (meaning without life) for it would rot, putrefie and ſtink, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But we ſhall prove firſt the burial of that Bodie of <hi>Christ, John</hi> 19. at the later end of the Chapter; his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>chap.</hi> 20. his ſhewing his hands and his ſide to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and after to <hi>Thomas;</hi> but to prove this fully, that it was the bodie that walked upon earth, he ſaith himſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 24 39. Handle me and ſee, for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones, as ye ſee me have. And that it is the ſame <hi>Jeſus,</hi> it is proved in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>The former Treatiſe have I made, O</hi> Theophilus, <hi>of all that</hi> Jeſus <hi>began both to do and teach, untill the day in which he was taken up:</hi> which proves that the doing and teaching <hi>Jeſus</hi> was taken up: and I affirm it was the bodie; for when he was upon earth he did no actions but with his bodie, nor ſpake words but with his tongue that is a member of that bodie, and that the ſame <hi>Jeſus</hi> was taken into Heaven is plain in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11. <hi>Ye men of</hi> Galilee, <hi>Why ſtand ye gazing up into Heaven? This ſame</hi> Jeſus, <hi>which is taken up from you into Heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as ye have ſeen him go into Heaven.</hi> [This ſame <hi>Jeſus</hi>] muſt be he who is ſpoken of in <hi>v.</hi> 1. who is not without the bodie, being the things that he ſpake and did were ſpoken and done with his bodie.</p>
            <p>And now it follows that I prove he is in Heaven, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. <hi>Seeing then that we have a great High Prieſt that is paſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Heavens,</hi> Jeſus <hi>the Son of God.</hi> And it is proved that this High Prieſt is not without the bodie, becauſe he is called a man, and I hope all men will ſay the bodie and ſoul is the man.</p>
            <p>And that this man continues for ever is proved in <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24. <hi>But this man, becauſe he continueth ever, hath an unchangeable Prieſthood.</hi> And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.3. <hi>It is of neceſſity that this man have ſomewhat alſo to offer.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>For if he were on earth, &amp;c.</hi> which proves that the manhood is in Heaven. And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. <hi>For</hi> Chriſt <hi>is not entred into the holy places made
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118688:6"/>
with hands, which are the figures of the true, but into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf, now to appear in the preſence of God for us.</hi> And if any doubt whither it is the man there ſpoken of, look in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.12. for the ſpeech is continued, and there it is ſaid, <hi>But this man after he had offered one ſacrifice for ſins for ever, ſat down at the right hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if any man doubt whither the man be now in Heaven, let him look into <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>And he ſhall ſend</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>which before was preached unto you, whom the Heaven muſt receive, untill the times of reſtitution of all things.</hi> Now <hi>Christ</hi> was preached a crucified <hi>Christ,</hi> ſo that the bodie muſt needs be in Heaven. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. <hi>We preach</hi> Chriſt <hi>crucified, unto the</hi> Jews <hi>a ſtumbling block, and unto the</hi> Greeks <hi>fooliſhneſs.</hi> It was the greateſt ſtumbling block that could be to the <hi>Jews</hi> in the world, to think that he that ſhould come to deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould firſt be crucified.</p>
            <p>Theſe things thus proved, let no man hereafter ſay, that that bodie of our Lord which was crucified without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is not in Heaven.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee how theſe men denie the Lord that bought them, if they denie that bodie that was crucified for them, for he bought Lordſhip over all things by his death; and ſo by that bodie that bled and ſuffered on the Croſs, and by that death became their Lord, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.7, 8, 9, 10. they denie the Being of it.</p>
            <p>And alſo they denie the Lord that bought them in the fifth miſtake of theirs, wherein they denie all Forms or Ordinances. There is nothing that <hi>Christ</hi> commanded as Lord over his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, that is to ſay, the Rules of Government that he appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to govern his choſen generation, his peculiar people, his royal Prieſthood with, but they denie: it and therefore theſe are they that ſtumble at the Word, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8, 9. Alſo they denie the love tokens that he left, the one that follows repentance from dead works, and faith towards God, as the firſt act of faith, building upon the foundation, I mean Baptiſm. The other the token of his death to be a remembrance of him untill he come, I mean the Lords Supper. And now let theſe that are <hi>Christs</hi> Enemies, that denie both Bodie and Rule of <hi>Christ,</hi> hear one
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118688:7"/>
loving reproof out of <hi>[It is written]</hi> which their Predeceſſors (I mean the Papiſts) would have taken from us in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue: and theſe men would take from us the virtue of it, that is to ſay, the ſharpneſs and ſweetneſs of it, by working upon us a diſlike of it. I ſay a reproof in love that if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they may be healed: the Scripture I reprove them by is <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>But thoſe mine Enemies which would not that I ſhould reign over them, Bring hither, and ſlay them before me.</hi> O that they would conſider the written Word that they deſpiſe, and examine themſelves whither they were not once Citizens, <hi>Luke</hi> 19 14. that is, whither they were not under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Citie that had for its Charter the written Word of God, when his Word and his Spirit that writ it had command of their ſouls. It is written is enough to humble a poor ſoul, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove a tender conſcience, to be a light to our paths, and a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to our feet, to make known ſin, and to command the Devils abſence; and hath it no power over you? Have you a ſpirit to guide you without a written Word? It is out of Gods govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then if it cannot be brought to the Law and the teſtimonies to ſee whither it ſpeak according to that Word or no, <hi>Iſai</hi> 8.20. Ye may be familiar ſpirits for ought I know. Do ye not weep and mutter? as <hi>Iſai</hi> 8 19. What muttering and uncouth howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is ammong ye, which we cannot but impute to a ſpirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word, if ye will not come to the Word to be tried? we are commanded to trie the ſpirits whither they be of good or no; and alas, how ſhall we do it, if ye denie both the written Word that is our Rule and Reaſon too, for you appeal from both? Alas, alas, what ſhall we do for you? we fear you will periſh eternally. And now that he is aſcended and gone into a far countrey, Do you not ſend meſſages after him, and ſay, Ye will not have this man rule over ye? for indeed ye denie both his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Word, that is to ſay, the written Word that was from God by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, even the written Word which is the Rule of Life and Love, ſealed and approved of by <hi>Christ;</hi> as alſo the Commandments of <hi>Christ,</hi> that he and his Apoſtles ordained, I mean Baptiſm to accompanie converſion and the whole order of communion in the Goſpel of God: to follow I mean thoſe Commandments that were not before <hi>Christs</hi> time
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118688:7"/>
and given out by none but himſelf and his Apoſtles, ſpoken of in <hi>John</hi> 15.10. <hi>If ye keep my Commandments, ye ſhall abide in my love, even as I have kept my Fathers Commandments, and abide in his love.</hi> Now I demand what diſtinction could <hi>Christ</hi> make here betwixt his and his Fathers Commandments, but that his were the Ordinances and Laws to govern his Church by: and in <hi>John</hi> 14.21. See what ſweet promiſes follows the obedience to <hi>Christs</hi> commands. And if they will cavil at them ſtill becauſe they are written, as if it were but the Letter, that which is written in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.37. <hi>If any man think himſelf to be a Prophet, or ſpiritual, let him acknowledg, that the things that I write unto you, are the Commandments of the Lord.</hi> By which Word in the Name of God I proclame, that thoſe men that diſown the written Word are not ſpiritual men, I mean, have not the Spirit of <hi>Christ;</hi> they may have the bewitching ſpirit of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> that may make them denie the uſe of their own Reaſon, becauſe they have not faith in the Root, as in 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And that we may be delivered from unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and wicked men, for all men have not faith:</hi> where the Apoſtle braves thoſe men that have not the uſe of Reaſon, to be wicked and void of faith.</p>
            <p>Who but the ſpirit of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> durſt not onely ſet their poſts by <hi>Christs</hi> poſts, but alſo countermand the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our Law-giver the Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were never any men appeared in the world ſo like thoſe that <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of in his ſecond Epiſtle, <hi>ch.</hi> 2.17. to the end of the Chapter, I pray you reade thoſe Verſes conſiderately; in <hi>v.</hi> 17. he ſaith, They are <hi>Clouds carried with a Tempeſt:</hi> What greater Tempeſt than ſo much ſpiritual violence as to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie all down afore them, without conſideration either of the written Word or the uſe of Reaſon. In <hi>v.</hi> 18. he chargeth them with <hi>ſpeaking great ſwelling words of vanity:</hi> he chargeth them alſo to <hi>allure through the luſts of the fleſh: The Fleſh luſteth</hi> or deſireth <hi>againſt the Spirit.</hi> Theſe deſire to overthrow the Writngs of the Spirit of God: he chargeth them likewiſe with <hi>much wantonneſs.</hi> What more wantonneſs than to ſhake off all Rules, that their own imaginations may have the full ſway: and if Mr. <hi>Pope</hi> doth not belie them, they uſe unſeeemly kiſſing in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118688:8"/>
heir open and publique Aſſemblies at <hi>Glaſſtiers Hall:</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> in the ſame Verſe makes the caſe dangerous to <hi>live in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> (that is, for want of knowledg of the Scriptures as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) although men have clean eſcaped the pollutions of the world through luſts. In <hi>v.</hi> 19. he ſaith, <hi>While they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption.</hi> None ever promiſed to themſelves ſo much libertie as theſe and the Ranters in being freed from the power and trial of the Word. And how greatly do they ſerve corruption in this their libertie when they diſclame the written Word, which is the check and bridle of corruption being overcome by libertie, and brought in bondage to that wicked libertie. In <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>The later end is worſe with them than the beginning:</hi> becauſe now they do that upon a religious account that before they did upon an ungodly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. The Lord bleſs every one of his from the condition of <hi>Chandler,</hi> who formerly was the Head of a Companie of Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, whoſe condition I dread to ſpeak of, it is known to almoſt all perſons hereabouts. And in <hi>v.</hi> 21. the ſame Apoſtle char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them with falling from <hi>the way of righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>a holy Commandment</hi> given <hi>unto them:</hi> which way of righteouſneſs ſtanding by a command of <hi>Christ</hi> muſt needs be the order of the Goſpel of God.</p>
            <p>Their ſpirit will perſwade them that they are not fallen from righteouſneſs, and therefore would juſtifie them.</p>
            <p>But he cannot juſtifie them in denying the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that was commanded by <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And it is apparant before God and Angels to all knowing men in Religion but themſelves, they or ſome of them are fallen from that. But I ſhall write no more at this time about the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of Ordinances, being I have writ more largely before in a little Treatiſe called <hi>[Diſobedience detected.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we come to the ſixth of their miſtakes, which at the outward or overly looking upon it, one would think it were a ſmall ſlight thing, but when we come to weigh it with [It is written] it is an heavie and ſad offence, I mean the not giving ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to men: which is contrary to the examples of good men and command of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the example of good men: <hi>Sara</hi> called <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118688:8"/>
Lord. The Angel of God which would not from God miſtake his meſſage, counſelled <hi>Hagar</hi> to ſubmit her ſelf to her Miſtris, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.9. <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant when he prayed to God and was heard, called <hi>Abraham</hi> his Maſter, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.11. And when his ſoul was in a ſpiritual frame, and his heart filled with praiſes to the living God, called him Maſter, <hi>v.</hi> 27. And to man alſo when he was declaring his meſſage he called <hi>Abraham</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>v.</hi> 34.35. <hi>Jacob</hi> when he had been newly wreſtling with God for a bleſſing, bowed himſelf ſeven times to <hi>Eſau, Gen.</hi> 33.4. and all his familie did obeyſance. <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren by revelation of his Dream, and that from God, which after came to paſs, did obeyſance to him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 44.14, 15, 16. <hi>David</hi> a man after Gods own heart, that had the Kingdom given him, but not yet in poſſeſſion, called <hi>Saul</hi> My Lord the King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.17. So that if theſe men ſhould tell us, honoring one another will vaniſh away in the reſtoration of all things; I let theſe men with <hi>David</hi> tarrie their time, that is, till they be in poſſeſſion of the reſtoration: and this did <hi>Christ,</hi> though he propheſied of the downfall of <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Ceremonies, and was that <hi>Chriſt</hi> that fulfilled them, yet he worſhipped in the Temple whileſt they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Paul</hi> after him. And by the way here is one note for the non-churches, though it be true that Forms and Ordinances ſhall ceaſe, yet let them tarrie their time and worſhip in them till <hi>Christ</hi> become. <hi>David</hi> calleth himſelf <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervant, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.23. and <hi>Davids</hi> wife by the counſel of the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.15. called My Lord the King. And <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet ſpeaking to <hi>David</hi> called him My Lord the King in <hi>v.</hi> 24. And <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet of the Lord ſpeaking to a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſaith, O King. So did the three Children at a time when <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was in the height of his wickedneſs, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17, 18. And <hi>Daniel</hi> at a time when he had received the greateſt mercie from God of ſalvation from the Lions ſaid, <hi>O King live for ever, Dan.</hi> 6.21. And <hi>Paul</hi> called <hi>Agrippa,</hi> O King, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.13, 19. and called <hi>Feſtus,</hi> Moſt noble <hi>Feſtus.</hi> So that we may ſee what was the practice of holie men, Angels and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, and that upon remarkable times, upon ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous occaſions. How far are theſe men from following the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of holie Writ? Surely as they denie the virtue of <hi>[It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten]</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118688:9"/>
ſo they are very careleſs in reading and obſerving what is written. And they that are their Proſelytes will be leſs know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being that their converters or rather perverters caſt an <hi>odium</hi> upon what is written.</p>
            <p>But now to come to the commands that they diſobey in this their practice. Firſt the Law that Gods finger writ, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Honor thy Father and Mother. Lev.</hi> 19.31, 32. we finde theſe words, <hi>Regard not them that have familiar ſpirits, neither ſeek after wizards, to be defiled by them; I am the Lord thy God. Thou ſhalt riſe up before the hoary head, and honor the face of the old man, and fear thy God; I am the Lord.</hi> Now the ſpeaking againſt familiar ſpirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> immediatly before the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving honor to men may intimate that wizards and ſuch as have familiar ſpirits uſe not to honor men; but I am ſure theſe two are linked together, being both ſins alike; for the command of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noring and fear thy God are joyned together in a ſentence; and theſe men by this Scripture denying to honor men in their ſeveral relations, do alſo therein denie to fear God. And you cannot ſay this command was aboliſhed ſince <hi>Christs</hi> time, for the Apoſtle ſtill approves of it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6 2. And <hi>Peter</hi> whoſe ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie was much oppoſit to theſe kinde of men in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16, 17. hath theſe words, <hi>As free, and not uſing your liberty for a cloak of maliciouſneſs, but as the ſervants of God. Honor all men, Love the Brotherhood, Fear God, Honor the King.</hi> Which may prove that the malitious Libertine feareth not God, nor ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for man. I could here bring a cloud of witneſſes, but let this ſuffice; as <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaking of perſons, I hope more filthie than theſe, <hi>Iude</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> addeth this to fill up their Ephah of wickedneſs, <hi>They ſpeak evil of Dignities, and despiſe Dominion.</hi> Alſo <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Give honor to whom honor belongeth.</hi> And in giving ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Go one before another. But you ſee there is enough in <hi>[It is written]</hi> to reprove thoſe that care not for <hi>[It is written]</hi> if they be not uncapable of reproof:</p>
            <p>And now I come to the laſt of their miſtakes, in admitting of none but perfect men into conjunction. In the firſt place we are ſure that <hi>Iohn</hi> writes to children, young men and fathers, and mindes degrees of attainment, 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.13. but theſe at one time wrought upon ſay that they are perfect, not minding ſuch a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118688:9"/>
perfection as is ſpoken of in <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. where a gradual at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment is ſpoken of; not as though I had already attained ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were already perfect; but I follow after, if I may appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that for which I am alſo apprehended of <hi>Christ,</hi> where he ſeemeth to ſtate the matter thus, 'tis true I am confident of Gods mercies, the act of <hi>Christ</hi> is done for me, he hath apprehended me, but I am not perfect, but I am a follower after perfection, and deſire and labor earneſtly to apprehend him. And in <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. he ſaith, <hi>Brethren, I count not my ſelf to have apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things which are behinde, and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before: I preſs toward the mark for the price of the high calling of God in Jeſus Christ.</hi> In which Verſes for fear any ſhould think he ſpoke in the perſon of another in the way of teaching, in <hi>v.</hi> 12. he avers it ſolemnly of it ſelf. In <hi>v.</hi> 12. as if he ſhould ſay, The price is great of that Calling of God, in which onely is perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (the Calling he had but the price he wanted) but I have it not, yet I preſs after it; and it is true, I muſt hit the mark for it. In which arguings of his he ſeems to engage the labor of all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoul, as his conſideration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> leſt he ſhould ſhoot beſide the mark: I weigh things (which is an act of reaſon) I eſteem all things as loſs. In <hi>v.</hi> 8. and his deſires, forcing labors, and gradual earneſt motion forgetting that which is behinde, and reaching out to that which is before. And in <hi>v.</hi> 15. he ſaith, <hi>Let us therefore, as many as be perfect, be thus minded:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, There is no other perfection attainable, and this is perfection; and let none ſay they are perfect, and affirm they are paſt this earneſt ſuit and purſuit after the things of <hi>Christ.</hi> God will reveal this unto him, that is, he will make him know it either here to his conviction or hereafter to his judgment; for it ſhall be revealed, <hi>viz.</hi> that there is no perfection that diſengages the man from purſuit with his labor of minde to attain in this life that which ſhall be enjoyed when <hi>Christ</hi> ſhall appear, for then <hi>we ſhall be like him:</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. And to back <hi>Pauls</hi> judgment <hi>Peter</hi> agrees with him, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. from 5, to <hi>v.</hi> 11. where he puts the living Chriſtian that has received all things that appertain to life and godlineſs; as in <hi>v.</hi> 3. upon his preſſing after perfection, namely, that they give all diligence. In <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; v.</hi> 10. again,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118688:10"/>
make their Election and Calling ſure: and when this is done, it is true, he promiſes them an entrance abundantly into the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> but no more but an entrance in this life, as if it were ſaid, 'Tis but an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance; and there will be always work for the preſſing motion of the minde, reaſon to conſider and deſire, and prayer to attain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to have a threefold witneſs, in <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Draw me, we will run after thee.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Tell me (O thou whom my ſoul loveth) where thou feedeſt, where thou makeſt thy flocks to feed at noon; for why ſhould I be as one that turneth aſide, &amp;c.</hi> where it appeareth that the Spouſe with an engaged reaſoning minde that ſhe may not turn aſide wreſtles with <hi>Christ,</hi> to draw her, to teach her; which implieth, that no ſuch perfection ſo as to take off a laboring to be perfect, is a life attainable here: but in their perfection they denie any man being under frailtie or capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs to ſin to be of their communion; it may be they do it from that place 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6. <hi>Whoſoever abideth in him, ſinneth not; whoſoever ſinneth, hath not ſeen him, neither known him.</hi> But they muſt view this whole Epiſtle, and they may eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him otherwiſe: as 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7, to the end, <hi>If we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the bloud of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin. If we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us. If we confeſs our ſins, he is faithfull, and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If we ſay that we have not ſinned, we make him a lyar, and his Word is not in us.</hi> Where it is proved, he that is in the light and hath fellowſhip with God is at that time under clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from ſin by the bloud of <hi>Christ,</hi> which is far from their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. It proves <hi>John</hi> writing in the preſent Tenſe that he and thoſe in communion with the Father and the Son were not freed abſolutely from ſin when he writ this Epiſtle, <hi>v.</hi> 8. In <hi>v.</hi> 9. In <hi>v.</hi> 9. that <hi>John</hi> and thoſe that have communion with the Father and the Son are forgiven their ſins after their confeſſion, this is far from their perfection. It may be ſaid then what was <hi>Johns</hi> meaning in <hi>chap.</hi> 3.6. I anſwer, he explaineth himſelf in 5.18. <hi>We know that whoſoever is born of God, ſinneth not; but he that is begotten of God, keepeth himſelf, and that wicked one touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118688:10"/>
him not.</hi> That wicked one is the ſin unto death, that muſt be there meant, for it is ſpoken of before, then <hi>Iohns</hi> meaning muſt needs be, that he that is born of God ſins not unto death; for in <hi>v.</hi> 16. he doth acknowledg that a brother may ſin a ſin that is not unto death, and yet obtain life. Their Speaker told me in their meeting, (that which had ſinned could not be ſaved) I told them, nothing could be ſaved but that which is capable of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which was man, who without ſalvation as under ſin he muſt be damned: and now I ſay there is nothing can be in man but it muſt be a part or a member of man, except it be God or the Devil. And it is abſurd and incongruous to think that will ſave God, he cannot receive ſalvation, for he is eternally happie. And I anſwer, the Devil ſhall not be ſaved, he hath ſinned the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſin. And by the way behold and conſider the vanitie of that ſpeech to the thing within man; but further that their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine may appear to be utterly againſt what is written, add ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther witneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. <hi>I ſee another Law in my members, warring againſt the Law of my minde, &amp;c.</hi> O what a conflict in a believers heart is here whileſt ſin appears? yet let not them think that we by this Doctrine nouriſh ſin; for when the Spirit of God and <hi>[It is written]</hi> hath diſcovered ſin in the ſoul it hath ſuch a conflict that it laments his wretchednes, and is violent for deliverance; and then there is a running to God by the Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to propitiate: the poor convinced ſinner needs none to purſue ſin unto death but himſelf by Gods movings, pardon, cleanſing from ſin, killing of ſin that it never riſe again, is then earneſtly implored at the Throne of Grace; and then the ſin-ſick ſoul can never be healed nor quieted without a ſmile of his heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Christ Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The denial of <hi>Christs</hi> Bodie is no where in the Word. The denial of his Ordinances is no where in the Word. Theſe men muſt needs then perſwade above what is written. Theſe two Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines cannot be preaching <hi>Christ</hi> crucified, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of them if they were true ſerves not for converſion, nor for building up, not making the man of God perfect. Therefore there is no ſervice done for God nor his Church in theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. But there may be much ſervice done for Satan and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice to themſelves, when they denie both Bodie and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118688:11"/>
of <hi>Christ;</hi> What greater denial can there be of the Lord that bought them? when they leave him neither Bodie nor Laws extant. When he hath no Laws he is no King; if no Bodie, no Being, but as he may be reſolved into the Father. So then there is none but God, there is no Son to give up a Kingdom to the Father; and when he hath done to be ſubject to the Father. The commands of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are thoſe that he gave, that is, which were not given before he came, that is to ſay, ſetting a Government for <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> to worſhip him in, and who ſo ever denies this though an Angel from Heaven let him be accurſed. And Satan may let theſe be pure and holie in regard of outward holineſs or juſtice between man and man, freedom from the pollutions of the world through luſt, if he can make them be of thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the Lord that bought them, this Error is ſin enough to hold them faſt cloſe in his claws to eternal damnation, they need not any more, (if mercie belong to them, the Lord give it them) and keep his elect that cannot be drawn away by the deceit of theſe evil times. Now if it be ſaid, Theſe men are ſpiritual and full of light: it may be ſaid, There may be deceits by ſpirit as well as in word or letter, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.2. And to my knowledg, theſe mens fore-runners the Ranters did ſpeak as ſpiritually as they, with words more like a ſpirit than a man, terrifying and diſturbing the hearers mindes. I hearing <hi>Frankling</hi> was not able, nor durſt go on to hear him, leſt he ſhould bewitch me; for though his words were piercing, I knew he ſpoke not the truth according to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which is our Rule of Trial, to prove <hi>Pauls,</hi> or Satans Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Theſe things being ſet home upon my ſpirit, and being freely perſwaded not onely of the truth thereof, but of the hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs and ſad conſequence of theſe great Errors and Miſtakes, wherein ye are detained by that ſpirit of deluſion; I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained out of my love to ye, many of whom I have known for ſome years, to communicate theſe lines to ye, not of any preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to your perſons, for my hearts deſire is that the Lord will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver ye from this ſpirit; and if there be any thing that may ſeem unacceptable, or more than once repeated, know it is for ſeveral purpoſes, but all for the good of your ſouls.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
